<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speech made to his excellency the Lord General Monck and the council of state, at Fishmongers-Hall in London. The thirteenth of April, 1660. At which time they were entertained by that honorable company. / Written by Tho. Jordan. After a song of difference betwixt the lawyer, the soldier, the citizen and the countrey-man. The chorus being ended. Enter the ghost of Massianello fisher-man of Naples.</title>
            <author>Jordan, Thomas, 1612?-1685?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.3[102]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885209</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182586</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182586)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C5:1[35]; A1:1[33]; A4:1[102])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speech made to his excellency the Lord General Monck and the council of state, at Fishmongers-Hall in London. The thirteenth of April, 1660. At which time they were entertained by that honorable company. / Written by Tho. Jordan. After a song of difference betwixt the lawyer, the soldier, the citizen and the countrey-man. The chorus being ended. Enter the ghost of Massianello fisher-man of Naples.</title>
                  <author>Jordan, Thomas, 1612?-1685?</author>
                  <author>Yolkney, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcut).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid over against the Anchor Inn in Little Brittain.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Is your peace just? What rock stands it upon? ..."</note>
                  <note>At end of text: Spoken by Walter Youkcny.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Albemarle, George Monck, --  Duke of, 1608-1670 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:182586:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>A SPEECH Made to His EXCELLENCY The Lord General MONCK And the COUNCIL of STATE, At Fiſhmongers-Hall in LONDON.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <date>The Thirteeth of <hi>April,</hi> 1660.</date> At which time they were. Entertained by that Honorable COMPANY.</head>
            <byline>Written by <hi>Tho. Jordan.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>After a SONG of difference betwixt the <hi>Lawyer,</hi> the <hi>Soldier,</hi> the <hi>Citizen</hi> and the <hi>Countrey-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <stage>The CHORUS being ended. Enter the <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of <hi>MASSIANELLO</hi> Fiſher-man of <hi>NAPLES.</hi>
            </stage>
            <lg>
               <l>IS your <hi>Peace</hi> juſt? What rock ſtands it upon?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> make the beſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If you gain <hi>Birthrights</hi> here by <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Slaughter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though you <hi>ſing</hi> now, you'l <hi>howle</hi> for ever after:</l>
               <l>Truſt my Experience, one that can unfold</l>
               <l>The ſtrangeſt trueſt Tale er'e was told,</l>
               <l>In my <hi>degree,</hi> few men ſhall overtake me,</l>
               <l>I was as <hi>great</hi> as <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> could make me;</l>
               <l>This <hi>heart,</hi> this <hi>habit,</hi> and this <hi>tongue</hi> to boot</l>
               <l>Commanded <hi>Forty thouſand Horſe and Foot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In three weeks time, My fortune grew ſo high</l>
               <l>I could have match'd my <hi>Fiſhers</hi> Family</l>
               <l>With the beſt <hi>Bloud</hi> in <hi>Naples: Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doath</hi> attended on my <hi>Tongue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till (by a quick verticitie of <hi>Fate</hi>)</l>
               <l>I find too ſon what I repent too late;</l>
               <l>And, though a <hi>Rebell</hi> in a righteous clothing,</l>
               <l>My glow-worm glories glimmer'd into nothing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus fell that <hi>Fiſher-man</hi> that had no fellow,</l>
               <l>I am the Wandring Shade of <hi>Maſſianello;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, ſince I was into <hi>Perdition</hi> hurl'd,</l>
               <l>Am come to preach this Doctrine to the world.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rebels though backs with Power, and ſeeming Reaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time and Succeſs, ſhall fell the fate of Treaſon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſtay! <note place="margin">
                     <stage>
                        <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e looketh up to the Picture of Sir <hi>William Walworth</hi> (who ſtab'd <hi>Jack Straw</hi>) that hangeth over the head of my Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</stage>
                  </note> what <hi>Picture</hi>'s this hangs in my ſight?</l>
               <l>'Tis valiant <hi>Walworth,</hi> the <hi>King-ſaving</hi> Knight:</l>
               <l>That ſtab'd <hi>Jack Straw:</hi> Had <hi>Walowrth</hi> liv'd within</l>
               <l>Theſe four Months, where had <hi>Jack the Cobler</hi> been?</l>
               <l>It was a bold brave deed, and act in Seaſon,</l>
               <l>Whileſt he was on the Top-branch of his <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But from that <hi>Shaddow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <stage>To the Lord General.</stage>
                  </note> dropping down My eye,</l>
               <l>I ſee a <hi>Subſtance</hi> of like <hi>Loyalty.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>IF long renowned <hi>Walworth</hi> had the fate</l>
               <l>To ſave a <hi>King, You</hi> have to ſave a <hi>State;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Paralle<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>And, who knows <hi>what</hi> by Conſequence? The Knight</l>
               <l>By that brave Deed, gain'd every man his Right:</l>
               <l>And you, by this, may gain each Man his due,</l>
               <l>Not onely Truſty Hearts, but <hi>Traitors</hi> too:</l>
               <l>He <hi>drew bloud,</hi> you did not; 'tis all one ſenſe,</l>
               <l>There's but a <hi>Straws</hi> breadth in the difference:</l>
               <l>He ſav'd the <hi>Town</hi> from being burnt, and <hi>You</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have reſcued it from <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Plunder</hi> too:</l>
               <l>He was this <hi>Companies</hi> good <hi>Benefactor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>You</hi> have been their <hi>Liberties Protector;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For which, I heard them ſay, they would engage</l>
               <l>Their States, and Blouds, and Lives againſt all rage</l>
               <l>That ſhall oppoſe Your <hi>juſt Deſignes:</hi> And that</l>
               <l>You are the welcomſt Gueſt, <hi>ever</hi> came at</l>
               <l>This Table; they ſay, All they can exhibit</l>
               <l>Is not ſo much a <hi>Treatment</hi> as a <hi>Tribute:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They call you the Firſt ſtep to <hi>England</hi>'s Peace,</l>
               <l>The True fore-runner of our Happineſs:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And, joyn'd with theſe great <hi>Councillors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <stage>To the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="4+ letters">
                           <desc>••••…</desc>
                        </gap>cil of St <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </stage>
                  </note> You are</l>
               <l>Our beſt <hi>Preſervatives</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>War.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You have a Loyal <hi>Heart,</hi> a Lucky <hi>Hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Elected for the Cure of this Sick Land,</l>
               <l>Who by <hi>Protectors</hi> and <hi>unjuſt Truſtees,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath been Enſlav'd, and brought upon her Knees:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We humbly pray this may be thought upon</l>
               <l>Before the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> Treaſure be quite gon:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hope you will (though <hi>Envy</hi> look a ſquint)</l>
               <l>When all is fit, Put a Juſt <hi>Steward</hi> in't.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Spoken by WALTER YOUKCNY.</stage>
            <lg>
               <head>CHORUS.</head>
               <l>Then may your fame out-live all Story,</l>
               <l>And prove a Monument of Glory;</l>
               <l>Kings and Queens (as Tribute due)</l>
               <l>On their knees ſhall pray for You,</l>
               <l>Whilſt all Truè hearts confeſs with Tongue and Pen,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Loyal Subject</hi> is the beſt of Men.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> over againſt the <hi>Anchor</hi> Inn in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
